Welcome back to exercise 4
First off, we have Task 12:
We should write a little
function that checks if a string that is
given as an input is a palindrome or not.
So whether it's the same word
read forwards or backwards.
We start with naming the parameter
xs, for example, and then
if we look at the lecture slides there was
a function that did a very similar thing.
It also checked for palindrome: xs == reverse xs
Nice and declarative.
And is this already a solution to our task?
Well, we have this test suite here so we can
just load it into ghci and test whether this
has the desired behavior.
So let's do that.
Load the ghci for Task 10.
Okay, and now we run main which
does some QuickCheck testing and tells
us whether we have done the right thing.
Okay, so the first test passes.
A single character is a palindrome
according to our function.
But the second test fails
because what we do is we
take a random character and a random
string and put the character in uppercase
in the front and unaltered in the back, and
it tells us that for this character being a
and string being the empty string our isPalindrome
function does not do the same right thing.
So let's check that.
isPalindrome of adding an upper
case to the front of the empty string and then
lowercase to the back; indeed does not yield True.
Okay, so in contrast to the palindrome function
from the lecture we should here take care of
upper- and lowercase and make sure
that the case does not matter.
So our 'isPalindrome' function
should be case insensitive.
Okay, so how do we do this?
We have this 'toUpper' and
'toLower' function to work with.
So what we have to do is transform the whole list
into, for example, the lowercase variant of
it before we check it against its reverse.
We could obviously choose uppercase
making everything uppercase as well
But let's go for lower.
So how can we do this; transform everything into
lowercase? Well, we use a list comprehension.
Getting every element from the
list and then applying toLower
to that element giving us this new list.
And then you just check this lowered list to
against its reverse and see if it's the same.
So if we reload this into ghci now
for isPalindrome of "Aa" we get True.
We can test it on some other palindromes like
this play around with the capitalization.
Seems to work.
Let's try the QuickCheck tests
again, and this time both succeed.
So this is a valid solution.
Is there another solution?
There's always another solution, at least in most
cases, so let's try to find another solution.
Let's define isPalindrome' :: String -> Bool
Let's start with the basic skeleton.
Let's again name the parameter.
And now what can we do?
Let's use the functions 'head' and 'last'.
If we check out ghci what they do.
We have head of some list -
let's take the list [1..5],
for example - head gives us
1 and tail gives us the rest.
And we also have 'last'
and 'init' and with these functions we are
going to try to implement isPalindrome now.
Because we can compare the first element against
the last and then cleverly use tail and init to
get the middle list and then
recursively call isPalindrome.
So what we're doing is we're getting the head of
the list and comparing it to the last element,
exactly what the palindrome is; if the first and
the last are equal, then it can be a palindrome.
And then we say okay, if this is the
case then also isPalindrome' of ...
And now we need the middle list
and for the middle list to get this
we cleverly combine init with tail.
Because if we take first the tail
and then the initial part of the tail we end up
with dropping the first and the last element.
So we're doing this here init (tail xs).
And now we need to take care of
the upper- and lowercase as well.
So toLower here and here.
And now ...
isPalindrome' of our example ...
Oh there's something wrong.
We have forgotten something.
Basically we're doing recursion
here and we're taking init and tail
but we're never checking for the empty list.
Because 'head' does not work on the empty list,
'tail' does not work on the empty list; 'init' ...
some work, some don't. (Actually,
none of the used functions do!)
If we take head [] gives an error,
tail [] is an error, init [],
and the last [] is also an error.
There are some functions like
this that work on empty lists.
None of these work on empty lists.
So we need to make sure that we actually catch
the case where the list is empty or small
enough where we don't need to do recursion.
So we add some guards.
Make this the
otherwise case, and
check the length, and we say the length has to be
smaller than 2; then we know it's a palindrome.
Because if it's empty, i.e., length
xs == 0, it is a palindrome;
and if it's just a single character,
it is also a palindrome by default.
Okay, now let's try this again.
Now we get the desired result.
We can again do this capitalization
thing, and now if we change
the function in these tests to
refer to our alternative solution,
load this up and run main. it passes all the
tests. So this is a valid solution as well.